Hi, it's part two, repair time here of
this Compaq IBM well, the world's first
IBM PC compatible machine. It's the
Compaq portable dates from 1984 and I'll
link in the video up here somewhere and
down below and at the end if you haven't
seen it. Anyway, we were debugging this
thing and we got down to the point where
the processor was actually reset. So, we
actually traced the problem down to the
basically the 8088 processor was
permanently in reset and the reset comes
from the 8284
clock driver chip here. This is the main
14.31818
megahertz
clock that is divided by this to give
you the 4.77
meg in here as well as other stuff and
the reset comes from here and the reset
pin that one there actually came from
the power good signal from the power
supply over here which is in the bottom
of the case. So, that's what's stopping
the processor from powering up. The
rails, the 5 volt rail, 12 volt rail
seemed okay, but apparently there is a
power good signal coming from it was the
second pin here on the power supply
connector. It was coming from in here.
So, let's get this power supply board
out and have a squeeze now.
It uses just these I have to take the
mains input out here. That's actually
welded soldered shut actually that
thing. So, it's probably just got a
filter in it or something like that.
Hopefully no refer caps that have blown
up, but anyway, mains does get in and it
does have these little clips here which
then could the board can slide out, but
it can only do that if you actually take
off not sure if you're going to be able
to see it in there.
Right down the bottom there in that
corner. Focus you bastard. There it is.
This little metal
springy clip that I had to undo, which
like it's like a locking pin or
something like that that locks the whole
power supply in place. It's rather, you
know, it's a clever and nice, but bloody
annoying. Anyway,
we should now be able to slide this
supply out. These connectors, I can't
damn well get them off. They're really
hard, but anyway, that's the plan cuz
everything else in this machine sort of
slid out. Everything's designed to be
modular in this machine, but they kind
of like didn't implement it very well.
Everything I tried to get out of this
had some kludge to it, and it was clunky
to get out, and I didn't like it.
Anyway, I'll get back to you. It does
come out somehow. There we have it.
There's our boards still attached to the
umbilicals,
but at least we can get in here and have
a visual inspection cuz the first thing
you want to do, well, first thing you
want to do is smell it, of course, but
visual inspection, make sure any of the
caps aren't failed because tag tantalums
like
these ones here
and these ones here, these are all tag
tantalums down
down here as well, absolutely famous for
catching on fire, and one of them
actually did when I switched this on. It
blew up. I'll see the previous video for
that, but not on this power supply did
it. On the
disk controller card. But anyway, we've
got electrolytic caps, and they all look
really good. They've got the vents on
top. None of those are bulging. Nothing
fancy going on there at all. I mean, you
know, could be
a ripple thing or something like that.
They could have certainly dried out and
have not died yet, but so they're mark
'em jobs. The orange ones, not sure, but
the silver ones are Sprague, made in
USA. They'll be fine. But no, of course,
if you were actually refurbishing this
thing and you were serious about, you
know, having this thing work for any
sort of extended period of time, you
would recap absolutely everything. All
the electros, all the tag channels. And
I didn't actually notice that before.
The silk screen would have been handy if
they put on the other side, but the silk
screen's buried under here. Sure enough
that second pin is PG or power good and
that's the one that's low. It's active
low and that's what's causing our
processor
to reset. But there's other rails. I've
only remeasured the plus five and plus
12 which are fine, but we've also got
minus five as well and minus 12. But
they're not needed for the processor.
But if the power supply of course has
any sort of you know, sensing stuff it
likely does to check the power rails. So
even if the negative five volt is
buggered, then it's going to just reset
the processor. Even though the processor
doesn't need the negative five volts.
So,
you know, better safe than sorry I
guess. It's just really annoying. I
mean, we can override that. We could
simply lift the pin, the second pin on
there and power this thing up and see if
it boots I guess. There's the back side
of the board there. It's a little bit
crusty.
So, I'll get in there with some high so
propyl and uh
clean that up. But you know, you might
look for dry joints,
you know, thermal cracked joints.
Actually, you know, thermal expansion of
the parts
as they power off and on over the years
and that can cause problems particularly
on like things like you know, the TO3
power transistors and stuff like that.
So, you want to get in there with a
little jeweler's loop or a microscope
and just uh inspect all those. And if
you're wondering what I use to have a
look at things like this that I can't
take over to say my Mantis or my Tagarno
microscope, I just use my times 10 macro
lens. This is an Opteka. This is what
all my close up shots that you see, I
just screw this on the front of my
camera and bingo, it gives me my
close-up shots like that. But, you can
actually just hold this near it and you
can actually get Look, you can get like
really good close-ups like that. It's
You know, it's it's really quite nice.
Highly recommend it. And sure enough,
you can see what
looks like possibly a cracked joint
there. It's like on the nut that holds
the TO3 in place. And the other one up
there looks like it's maybe
something similar, but I actually
measured those and they seem fine, but
that could be a potential intermittent
source.
Uh so, you'd want to
resolder those as a minimum. So, I just
powered it back up and of course the 5
and 12 V rails work, but sure enough, 1
2 3 4 5 pin number five or fifth one
from the end, that's supposed to be -5 V
and -12 V is not there either. So, yeah,
both negative rails gonski. Um and
that's why power good is not coming on.
So, we have to look at the negative
rails and here's where it gets like
really annoying. Um they're in here. Um
so,
and it's like just populated with all
these physically tall and dense parts.
These are probably the output filter
caps for it. The LM338
there, that is a positive voltage
regulator. So, that's almost certainly
not the negative rail there, but yeah,
little switching jobby in there perhaps
for the negative rail. So, it's just
really annoying from an access point of
view. And as
always with Murphy, if you have a look,
the fifth pin down there, that's
actually the -5 V which I'm trying to
trace. And of course, it doesn't go on
the neck bottom, does it? So, you can't
see where it's going to and I can barely
see down in there.
So, actually before I muck around on the
power supply, I thought I'd actually
power this board up with the bench
supply and then just start change the
reset pin. So, I've got it hooked up to
the bench supply here. I'm only
generating the 5 volts and 12 volts. In
fact, probably don't even need to
generate 12 volts and by looks of this,
I've turned it's on at the moment. The
12 volts is drawing nothing. So, like
the minus 5 and stuff like that is not
really needed for just getting the
processor and stuff like that working, I
believe. Anyway, it is drawing 1.6 amps
here and if I actually
reset it, put that to ground, 1.519
and switch it on, 1.577.
So, it draws a little bit more
power when it's going, but anyway, let's
measure some clock, shall we? There's a
reset pin. It's low.
There's our clock pin. That's uh that'll
be 4. Yeah, 4.77 megahertz. There it is.
Yeah, no wuckers. And let's look at some
bus activity, shall we?
It's just randomly, yep. That looks like
bus activity. Bus activity. More bus
activity.
Uh whatever that pin is. Sorry, I can't
remember all the pin outs off the top of
my head.
But yeah, this looks like
classic bus activity. So,
it's certainly doing something.
So, what I'm going to do now is plug in
the
video card in here cuz it shouldn't
Well, the video card might need the
positive and negative rails. Anyway,
let's just plug it in and see what's
what. All right, there we go. I've
plugged it in. Haven't hooked up monitor
yet, but we're getting significantly
more current draw. Look at that. The
video card's drawing huge amounts. I
mean, I like we're now 4 amps. Uh that's
just nuts. Drawing a lot more than the
processor is, and we're drawing
something on the 12 volts. And I'll
switch it on.
And getting an absolutely nothing on the
video output there. So, zippity-doo-dah.
Okay, we're still getting
bus activity there. That's a processor
bus activity. So, it's not like it's
being loaded down or anything like that,
but we're certainly getting
nothing on the video out, but I don't
have those other rails, so that could be
it. Okay, I've got uh minus five here.
And minus five's drawing nothing. Zip.
Okay, I got uh minus 12 as well, so I've
got all four rails there. Just set them
to nominal like half amp current limit,
whatever. So, whoa. Now we're going in
the current limit. Negative rail there.
Oh, no. No, there we go. No, it's good.
Maybe that was just a power on thing.
So, reset it.
Cuz I don't have a power on reset. So,
they're both drawing zero.
Negative five and negative 12, so and
I'm getting nothing on the video, so
that's still not going to help me. Even
if I fix my main power supply,
um
it's pointless because um this thing,
while the processor's working, the
video's not. So, once again, like as I
said, uh
I'm not sure if you have to make me set
some jumpers or something to get a
composite video out. Maybe I can check
uh some of the RGB
uh out here, perhaps. Okay, I've no idea
which pin's what. Hello. That looks like
a sync. That's definitely synchy. There
we go. Yep. Whoa. That's 50 hertz. Yeah,
getting stuff. There you go. 18 18 and
1/2 kilohertz.
That certainly looks like the
horizontal. Okay, it looks like we are
getting horizontal and vertical sync
there. There we go. We're getting
something in there.
That looks maybe like some video data.
Probably only one color
because that's all you need. When you
boot up, you probably just getting like
a text,
you know, a monochrome like one color
text image. So, that sort of makes
sense. So, it looks like
that works. So, this
uh
I think this machine's working. Um and
if we actually hooked up the CRT, but
I've got to put all the boards back in,
I think, to get all the CRT working
again. It'd be a mess to try and do that
outside of the case, I think. So, yeah,
that's a bit tricky. I wish I could get
that damn composite working. And by the
way, kids, don't try this at home. I'm a
professional.
Now, apparently, uh DIP switch five and
six on the main board here, these
actually set the uh startup video mode.
And it's currently set to uh CGA
80-column mode. So, that's interesting.
I might try MDA, which is both of them
off. So, I will do that and repower.
Okay, I'm getting the same horizontal
and vertical
there.
So, 18 and 1/2 K, but that data
does look significantly different. It
was less populated before, but I'm still
getting no composite output signal at
all. Now, here's something interesting.
I was just playing around with
measuring the signals again because I've
got a uh capture card, which we'll talk
about in a minute. But, I'm using the
case of the uh composite output
connector here as ground. And I was
using that uh before to actually probe.
But, now, if I actually probe these
signals, let me just do a a resetty.
Let's actually probe
these signals again. Look at this.
See how it's just dropping down there?
It's got some 50 hertz crap, all sorts
of stuff on there.
Right? Look at that. You see? And then
it's just it's just dropping down and
down and here's a sync.
See?
Look at that. It's just going down and
down and down and down. Now, what when
you see a signal like that and look it's
just rising up. When you see a signal
like that, that's indicative that the
ground is actually doing nothing. So, if
I disconnect the ground and measure that
again, you'll see it's doing the same
thing, right?
So, our ground is Why is that no longer
grounded?
Uh Beulah? Beulah?
So, if I actually measure
that compared to what I know is a ground
pin here,
it it's just not connected. It is not
connected at all. That is like
what?
What the?
It what I I swear it was before. That's
why I used it. I would have measured it.
It's actually been some quite some time
since I shot this video because I just
acquired a um
CGA uh to V VGA uh converter card and I
was just about to hook up all the
signals. I was determining where the
signals were and I
what?
And sure enough, if I measure it um
this bracket and of course which is
electrically connected uh to the ground
of the composite connector and also to
the shell of the uh CGA output
connector, then uh yeah, I'm getting
like um nothing. It's just like like 40,
50 meg, something like that and then it
is sort of like goes open compared to
ground. So, I have no idea how I was
measuring those signals before. Has been
a couple of weeks, but I got like I
don't know. Um I
scratching my head. Anyway, um
what I did is went and ordered a uh CGA
and EGA and YUV to VGA converter and
this is actually uh quite nice. It's got
the VGA in, it's got uh the component in
as well, and it should be able to do the
CGA, hopefully. Um and and it's got a
very came with a very nice little cable,
which then I've uh connected up to uh
pin headers here, so I can just slide
these on. Got to uh find which pins is
what again. I know that that one's
ground as in 5-V ground. I've buzzed
that one out. Um uh so I'll just uh
remeasure that now using that as the
ground pin, and uh
anyway, yeah, we'll get these signals
and we'll see if we can get a uh CGA
output signal from this thing. Actually,
it's a really quite frustrating that
there's no really easy ground points on
this thing that you can just hook your
scope probe up to, um you know, without
danger of you know, you can go on to
maybe one of the pins of a tag tent or
something like that. You know, that's
why um you know, you generally like pick
a
uh ground connector like a
you know, a a bracket like that. So,
when you're designing boards like this,
just make sure you include like a a nice
handy ground reference loop or pin or
something.
Er. Unfortunately, I'm getting
zippity-do-dar on this. No signal. Um
so, I've got to muck around with this
thing, but the menu um
yeah, I can't make heads or tails out of
that. I might need a cheat sheet, so
we'll see. Um there is an auto button.
Maybe I can press and hold auto or
something.
I don't know. I I am getting I'm getting
horizontal sync, vertical sync, and I'm
getting something on the green signal.
So,
yeah, I don't know. There's some
adjustment pots in there, maybe. Bugger,
I just read the manual for this thing um
or the specs on the eBay or whatever,
and it tells me that it's only 14 and
1/2 kHz to 16 and 1/2 kHz. We've got 18
and 1/2 kHz here.
D'oh! Winner, winner, chicken dinner,
green screen, and oh, I had to change
the mode of the board to RGB-S.
Um, and that worked a treat. So, there
it is. Um, I don't know what these are
okay. I assume they're Erica's 301, 401,
601.
Um, you know, we've got nothing and
course there's diskette error, but this
thing works. There you go. It boots.
Woohoo! Winner, winner, chicken dinner.
Um, that well, as you'd expect because
we were seeing video signals there. So,
yeah, no worries. But, hold on to your
hat.
If I use the ground down on this board
and I probe our composite output
we now have a signal.
Why weren't we getting a composite
signal before? Look at that. That is
going to work a treat. So, if I
hook this monitor back up to the
composite out, I have no doubt that
it'll work. What the
Whoa! Glitch in the matrix there.
So, I just change this back to AV here
and let's see if we Oh,
yeah, it's not as good, is it? It really
doesn't like that.
Uh,
that's yucky. Yucky, yucky.
Um,
so, yeah, modern monitors, they're
probably not very good at this sort of
thing. Meh, who knows? But, uh, yeah,
that's working a treat. And as we, uh,
saw before, it doesn't take any power on
the, uh, minus five and minus 12 volt
rails. So, really, to get this thing to
boot, um, I don't even need to fix that
power supply, uh, in this thing. All I
need to do is force that or break into
that line, force it, uh, high, and that
power good line, force it high, and
assuming that all the CRT circuitry and
everything works, it'll it should just
work a treat or at least the composite
output will work and we'll be able to
see that. At least we can read it, I
guess. Okay, I think the reason that the
composite is working now is because I
have been mucking around with these dip
switch settings and I which changes the
graphics modes and I think there's only
one that seems to work. Oh, okay. It
just takes some time to boot. Let me uh
Let me show you that.
Go like that and there's no composite
output
for quite some time at time this puppy.
Come on. You can do it and it will
eventually get there.
I believe or it did last time.
So, come on.
So, maybe I was a bit too impatient
before
about checking for video signals. There
we go. Yeah, it eventually just pops up.
Yep. So,
I you know, it's going through memory
checks or something like that before it
displays any before it even enables like
the video signal's not even enabled
until literally the text pops up. So,
there's no sync there. There's no
nothing. Okay, I've confirmed that the
only mode that actually seems to work is
dip switch
five off and six on which is I believe
CGA 40 column mode and that's the only
one that will give me the composite
output and work with this CGA to VGA
converter card as well. So, anyway, I'm
going to leave it set to that. So, that
at least gives me a baseline to get this
puppy up and running from now on. But
really, I didn't have any doubt that the
board would have worked cuz I found with
these vintage computers like just you
know, when you're talking about like TTL
stuff unless you have an exploded
tantalum cap like we had in the first
video, something like that. Really, the
you know, the silicon's actually quite
robust and you know, even after all this
time the mask ROM uh still works. You
know, that's all just fine and
everything's hunky-dory. The RAM in it
still works and everything's hunky-dory.
So, um yeah, I might have to look at
I'll look up those codes, but anyway,
like the thing works, the processor
works, everything all the video card
works. And yeah, everything's sweet. So,
no real surprise. I knew I I was pretty
confident. You know, I was like 90%
confident when I get this board out and
power it up from a bench supply, it'll
probably boot. And sure enough. So,
there you go. I'm going to leave this
video at that cuz I've run out of time
today. I will do the power supply
troubleshooting another day, but we at
least got this puppy up and running
using the external
um monitor output here. And I have
checked there are signals on the CJ
monitor
CJ connector as well. So, I should be
able to you know, if I assemble the
thing and the CRT doesn't work and I
can't get that working or I don't want
to get it working, I can at least hook
on an external monitor without having to
you know, hack into the internal header
connector here, but there you go. I hope
you like that. Um so, yeah,
I've got so two more unknowns as well. I
definitely know the power supply is
faulty. So, I need to fix the power
supply, but as I said, like the minus
5-V and minus 12-V rails on here draw
absolutely nothing. So, in terms of
getting this thing working, unless you
want to use like a serial port or
something like that, maybe where it
might use that
those voltages. I don't you know, all of
the disk drives and stuff like that.
Uh possibly and also the CRT as well.
They may only be for the CRT. So, you
know, who knows, but yeah, so to get the
So, probably to test the CRT, I reckon
I'm probably going to need to fix the
power supply first. So, that needs to be
the next step and then
check to see if the CRT works and get
this whole thing
restored eventually. It's one of those
time things. Anyway, that's it for
today. So, if you liked it, please give
it a big thumbs up. As always, discuss
down below.
Catch you next time.